foreign [Music]
I was thinking about
um
in regards to I don't know the innovator
talks about seeing a bird
and hitting it
and then thinking
along the rise of
it is the same thing that I'm seeing and
hearing even without without
experiencing it the thing through two
different senses even just one like
seeing a thing like three a bird it is
it exists and I see like the image of
this thing
that is this thing existing behind this
image which I'm seeing yeah and that's
basically the the idea of the external
objective World independent of
my experience of it but you realize
it's a contradiction in terms because if
you're seeing it
it's expensed and if it weren't
experienced you couldn't even talk about
it but how do you know then that there
isn't a real world behind
you don't but you can only assume
you can't know that there is neither can
you know that there isn't
so there might be
so then it might not be a contradiction
yeah but you could never find that
sure but that's one one thing to to not
be able to find out another thing is to
say it's a contradiction
consideration requires you to know that
there isn't
yeah what I mean is that it's a
contradiction thinking that you can talk
about it or think about but we are
talking about
see we are clarify something yes that
external world
that you cannot know
as independent of your experience
that you can only know on the basis of
your experience um
um
yes there is a contradictory aspect to
something what I'm saying is
what I'm saying is
uh you can't say there isn't that world
out there because you don't know that
and you can't say that there is because
you don't know that all you know is the
result of the experience because see you
can start saying no there is the public
World form an object to the senses are
really such we all perceive them as a
collectively in my experience it's just
this sensory impingements of these forms
now you could say oh there isn't such a
world it's all in my mind it's all my
it's all in my mind it's all my
experience such World cannot exist
but that would also be wrong now to say
so both go a bit too far
um
so where is the contradictory aspect in
regard to those two statements what is
the contradiction so it's not the
existence or non-existence of the world
because that cannot be known so you
don't know whether there is something
outside of yourself or there isn't the
mistake is is this
in that statement this this self this
extra temporal yeah so the mistake the
emphasis is on on your conceivings and
the mistake there is see I don't know
whether there is something outside or
not means I am assuming outside exactly
I just cannot decide on the content of
that outside yet that outside assumption
is only known on the basis of this
internal experience by me
so the notion of outside is a
contradiction in terms not the world or
not the world or the world exists or
doesn't exist or both exist it neither
exists and that's exactly what a Buddha
would not answer those questions in the
suitors oh is the word Eternal I does it
exist on its own independent of our
experiences in the individuals does it
carry on its own or is the world and
noticed not
Eternal and you wouldn't answer that
because either way you assume the
outside you assume there is this space
outside of your experience as a whole
inside of your Sixth Sense base
which is then populated by these forms
and so on or not
so just the conceiving of outside in the
base of your statement there is the
world outside there isn't the world
outside you're conceiving of the outside
is the problem
that's the contradiction
yeah so the ish
the fact that you think that you can
refer to it would you not say that well
no no you can you can you can refer to
it you can think it but you you don't
necessarily have to conceive it as an
outside as first and this second to it
you have to start seeing it as a
phenomenon so when you're referring to
the outside you recognize the debts
Within so the point where I'm kind of
trying to to sort of emphasize here is
you should not start believing that I
must stop thinking about outside because
every thinking of outside is the
conceiving you can't stop thinking about
side you are the outside you are the
perversion of perception so to speak
of the ownership
but what you can do is start recognizing
that the phenomenon of outside of this
experience
as real as it is whichever way it feels
whichever way it's perceived is within
the enduring experience as a whole so
instead of trying to manipulate how you
refer to outside you actually want to
develop a greater context that includes
even the most
external sense of experience that you
might have in regards to sight sounds
male taste touches oh but it's that's as
such is real and is such a phenomenon
it's my experience as a whole it's the
five aggregates
so you want to want to broaden your
context as opposed to fix the notion of
outside about uh this analogy of a parasite like
about uh this analogy of a parasite like
the parasite is real like as such yeah
in the sense so yeah so it's not denying
that there is a parasite no it's it's
really seeing as a parasite and that
that means yeah exactly putting it in
the context putting it against the right
backdrop so to speak and right backdrop
would be that hold on I have to have the
notion outside the world exists after me
the world will continue existing the
world existed before but all those
Notions are on the basis of conceiving outside
are on the basis of conceiving outside
of this experience as a whole yet they
are experienced the whole I mean when
you say all the world exists will exist
after my death that is your thought Here
and Now
what you are confined with what you're
experiencing it within these five
Aggregates you're still thinking your
thoughts on the basis of your Sixth Sense base
on the basis of your Sixth Sense base
experience
and as such that is within the enduring
five Aggregates but like ignorance is
beginning this so you you already are
like it's not like yeah yeah it's not
like you didn't do it and then you
started one morning yeah yeah and that's
the whole like like it is exactly
exactly yeah so he conceives in a part
uh from he could see it as mine
fundamentally so all these subtle uh
conceivings of outside first the second
second is first
in in kind of in in all areas of your
five cents experience and six and and
the mind uh all that kind of adds up
because it's beginningless
uh and the Practical result of that is
me and the world
things that are mine and I am sense of I
am sense of ownership sense of self
that's the result of these conceivings
but again if you read the mullah again
somebody might assume okay so I must
individually undo these little things
that's impossible they're just subtle
aspects that precede
that precede
your attitude of mind
so undo the attitude of mine in regard
to the five cents base and the thoughts
to undo the attitude just to the extent
of mind so you're not undoing the
thoughts just there is a thought of the
external world
undo Here and Now ownership of the
experience as a whole in regards to the
thought of the external world
that will maintain the balance of
thoughts sights sounds smell taste
touches and in them is Just Thoughts
sights sounds maltest touches
that's it
not too much not too little but it all
converges on that sense of mind so you
want to fulfill them all about you
basically practice not mine in regard to
everything top to bottom past future
present doesn't matter in what direction
whatever has arisen whatever is real as
such is an image is a feeling is a
perception not mine to the extent that it for as
not mine to the extent that it for as
long as it isn't yours it won't be mine
and then the next thing and then the
next thing and then the next thing
and you would have you would have
diminished all of the concealings from
them so what would be a necessary
prerequisite for practicing not mine in regard to
for practicing not mine in regard to
everything sight sounds melted such as
thoughts uh while they're endured
what would be the necessary prerequisite
what you have to do in order to for this
practice to even become intelligible
established virtue yeah like and I'll
keep talking about it for example
because it's easy to hear this okay so
I'll start doing this yet your whole
physical Behavior verbal Behavior pretty
much completely unpurified
still polluted not cleared from
blemishes those are the contradictions
of mine of outside of last diversion
delusion you are conceiving the subject
exactly so if you're perpetuating
conceivings through your actions and
contemplating on the level of Mind are
Mindful and not mine that's that doesn't
work recognize that
recognize that
your views are
the result perpetuated through your
actions exactly and the result of those
unless and there are more much more
coarse and could not even be recognized
as use until you stop stop acting in
those ways absolutely and only when you
stop acting in those ways can you
recognize oh actually just by doing that
without even thinking about it that's
the view that I'm affirming basically
yeah through development of virtue and
sense restraint
you are then looking at
at the bigger picture
and now if within that you start making
effort to cultivate the attitude of not
mine I mean as I said in whatever is felt
I mean as I said in whatever is felt
whatever is perceived so again it's not
about shaping manipulating or changing
what is felt or what is perceived it's
about extending the attitude of not mine in
extending the attitude of not mine in
regard to the whatever precious felt
whatever perception is being perceived
so I show God the attitude of not mine
that's it that's my work that's my
threshold that's I don't I don't go past
that point
that's the Gateway
and you can that's exactly why the
Buddha then did encourage the noble
disciples or Haya who have sort of uh accomplished
or Haya who have sort of uh accomplished
himself in virtue
a sense restraint he said okay you
should thus go around in your day-to-day
existence and every whatever you
experience you should regard this is not
mine this is not I am
and the reason why it's in that order
this is not mine this is not I am
uh it's because your sense of I am your
sense of self
is the result
of unquestioned
ownership and taking things as mine the
attitude of mine for me and attitude of
mind is the result of uh attitude for me
so that's like a subtle refinement of
the same thing so not for me not mine
not I am
do I need to repeat as a mantra no
I need to repeat it if I forgot about it
but even then I don't do it for the sake
of repeating it I do it for the sake of
re-establishing that context of oh not
mine not for me in regard not for me exactly
not for me in regard not for me exactly
so there is this feeling present and
there is trying to pressure me to act
not for me the pressure to act not like
another mind feeling impermanent and
each and each and no no don't try and
get rid of it it's permanent it's real
it's going to pressure me forever that's
not a problem the problem is if I take
it as mine at any point of that eternity
that's when it becomes a problem if you
if I don't take it as mine well
eternity is seen as impermanent he's
seen as unable so what's the problem
so you are free from the Eternal samsara
there you go
so you know the world is presenting
it's presented as for you
it's pointing all pointing at you
pressuring you trying to move you uh
feelings uh things that as I said you
perceive memories future plans doesn't matter
memories future plans doesn't matter
it's all for me for me for me and you
just take for granted that oh there must
be this me there must be this guy that
all these things point at
but if you as well that's another
thought that's for me conceiving the
image of myself the image of a guy there
the owner of this is another thing
that's for me which means oh so I could
actually disown him people was asking
you know is there that external world or
is it just a mind or you know where am I
in in the position of this this world
that lasts for forever and it goes to
these cycles and then when I die and
then I go to this realm and that's realm
I travel within that and so on and this
and that and the other the answer to all
of those questions
is there is suffering and there is
freedom from it
if you have such questions after you
would have fully resolved
liability to suffering so after you're
in other hand
then you can come and we can talk about
it everything else
robes doesn't he just robes he says the
Buddha's wrong or something like that
and uh
I will disrobe or
unless what it tells me whether the
world is external or Eternal or yeah
and then the Buddha says well did I ever
say I was going to tell you those things
yeah
yes is that similar to The Arrow you get
shot a person gets shot by somebody
they bring a surgeon that's that's
really there right there and to to treat
him and save his life
by pulling the arrow dealing with what
must be dealt there and then without
wasting any time
but he won't let him do that
he won't let him do that
he won't follow his instruction to get
the arrow out until he finds out who
shot him why he shot him how tall was
the person that shot him what was his
political affiliation what was his
religion why was he why did he shoot him
why was his childhood what were the
reasons for it so and then he does yeah
bleeds out so the only reason he's
asking is questions because he has been
shot yeah yeah he's suffering yeah I need to
yeah yeah he's suffering yeah I need to
figure it out because I'm suffering
those questions only arise because those
questions are the habits
and mental sort of patterns that you
developed on a kind of experiencing
suffering not knowing how to deal with
it yeah so coming out of suffering is a
broader intention to
any intention for example asking that
question or yeah I mean yeah yes the
broadest intention is yeah you realize
this is whatever like see if he if he
were to have time to reflect there while
he was dying and bleeding out because he
shot with an arrow he would realize wait
but the only reason I'm asking all these
questions is because this Arrow hurts me
and the only ways of me in the past
dealing with any pain is finding
satisfaction through senses or or
thinking and justifications assumptions
and Views that's the sole reason for
those things that I was doing them he
was just to cover up and manage
suffering so
there is a surgeon right in front of me
who says no he can actually save my life
and it seems that
he can
and the only thing he's asking me is to
refrain wasting time on those questions
and actually start practicing
like you I can have those questions
but no I'll put them aside I'll put my
mind thinking those questions I'll put
that aside while I'm doing what needs to
be done yeah you don't have to get rid
of them yeah so when people start asking
such questions pretty much the only
thing like they would the main thing
that would determine whether there is
even a whether there can even be a
conversation taking place is do you keep
the precepts are you celibate are you
strained are you guarding your sense
those are you moderating eating yeah and
then you would be able to understand the
place where those views are the roots of
those questions even if you're
mistakenly asking them you could
actually then understand
why that is wrong from the point of view
of practice but if a person is not
making any effort or minimal effort or
occasional effort not purified in virtue
not guarding the sense does but it's
revolving and emphasizing these
questions all the time any answer to
that it's not a practice it's not a down
my won't make a difference that's often
like people would kind of have the same
attitude towards oh what's the Buddhist
perspective on doing such and such thing
in such a such circumstance there is no
Buddhism Buddhist perspective is
suffering and freedom from it which
means Buddhist perspective is uprooting
of the four upadhanas uprooting of
sensuality abandoning of Desire
overcoming of attachment that's the
Buddhist perspective oh yeah but no what
do I do like if this happens and I see
that well if you're not free From Desire
not free from attachment not free from
ownership whatever you do will be wrong
so the Buddha wouldn't be helping them
in any way by indulging no you might
help them in worldly like somebody's not
interested in practicing the Dharma and
tell me what to do well keep the
precepts be a good person don't harm
others do that but see they don't ask
the questions like that people usually
ask the question is no no from the
dhamma point of view there is no dhamma
point of view that tells you how to lead
your household life dhamma point of view
tells you you have to abandon it you
have to abandon everything approve the
all of the attachment to be free from
craving that's the dhamma point of view
there's no compromise so somebody just
ask you is it I can advice how to live a
skillful laylife sure but don't confuse
that for the time of practice or coming
from the Dharma practice because it
doesn't so again with these questions
the principle of sensory strain comes
first applies even to these thoughts
even to these like just just mental
processes of oh who shot me why he shot
me and all of this always like wait but
see in order to overcome the pain
because of which I'm asking these
questions I need to stop emphasizing
those questions first it's it's it's
scratching you're just scratching yes in
the mind it's an expression it's a it's
a scratch exactly so you have you have
your physical scratches and so on verbal
ones but yeah this is a mental one and
then it's oh I have to actually stop
and the other pressure see because it's
going to be like pressure of Doubt but
why who why
why did I do
and he's like yeah well that pressure
those thoughts has to remain and I have
to endure them and not actually give in
to yeah let me just answer and resolve
this and that's how I will get closer to
uprooting the pain
because if you have been withdrawn from
its efficiently then yes you would be
able to apply what the Buddha said oh
yeah take it is not mine not for me not mine
take it is not mine not for me not mine
not I am
even stuff that is
it could have not been anyone be
and either way he can't be for me either
way it cannot be mine
and basically since restraint is done
the necessary basis for for even
applying for being able to apply that
attitude yeah yeah because those things
that you have to give up just in order
to establish basic sense of strength are
the things that you be most
pressure there into taking as your own
so well there is a reason exactly those
things always come with the pressure the
ownership is maintenance
craving
and the only reason again that you would
go act out of pressure
is because
it's painful
if you stop and think about it it's like
wait but why what is so bad
in those following Central design
like why don't I do it just for fun
yeah not follow why not just for fun be
celibate not eat in the afternoon leave
withdrawn from Central pressures just
for fun why don't I do it
you know I consider everything is not
for me even even at least that for later
just just for fun let me just not do
those those act out of those pressuring
things why nobody does that just for fun well
why nobody does that just for fun well
because it's very painful
I was like well that's surely it tells
you it's a problem
if something is basically forcing you
through pain to maintain it
that's um that's not a good deal
but it's and what would help just to
think about it yeah so you just of
course exactly so even thinking about it
theoretically abstractly it's painful
and then you you dismiss the even the
possibility of that you could do it yeah
but say say you do think about it and
say you do realize yeah this is painful
isn't it and why am I maintaining
if you stop doing it it's like what
what do you have to lose
what would change
so if you're not acting out of
pressuring sensualities
and you're in the pressure
feels like all this pain will last
forever if I don't scratch the edge but
then you still don't scratch ditch
you don't know this lab but well then
yeah then the pressure starts to
diminish it has to and you kind of know even
it has to and you kind of know even
before you start that it would
just maybe not as quickly as you would
want it to
but it does start to diminish because it
requires your input it inquires fueling
it requires maintenance
and you stop feeding it
and again that's what I said it is
possible even for an outsider outside of his
even for an outsider outside of his
teaching his dispensation to become
fully free from this sensuality
through not feeding it
overcome the pressure and see the actual
ridiculous trapping
trapping
devious nature of it
and be completely dispassionate towards
it see it as a trap
a ridiculous trap
so then this passion is
directly proportional to your seeing of
the Trap of the nature of the Trap of uh
yeah but I think practically you could
say this passion is directly
proportional to your ability to endure
the pain
and of the pressure and that would then
reveal the views yeah